A Guide to the History Harvest Collection, 1880-2012
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
History Harvest Collection, 1880-2012
Special Collections, James Madison University
5030
605 Digital Images
Under the direction of Dr. Andrew Witmer, students in the spring 2012 Introduction to U.S. Religious History Class, in partnership with Special Collections, worked to compile a digital collection of local religious artifacts. The class hosted a "History Harvest" in which local community members brought in items of religious significance to be digitized and shared with the community via JMU Libraries.
JMU's HIST 363 Intro. to US Religious History
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Currently, the majority of collection is only digitally available in the Special Collections reading room, no physical access to the scanned originals
Acquisition Information
This collection was obtained during the History Harvest on April 14, 2012 from individual donors.
Provenance
Donors were interviewed on site by students for background information about their items
Biographical Information
Students of Dr. Andrew Witmer’s Introduction to U.S. Religious History class planned and carried out a History Harvest in the spring of 2012. The purpose of this event was to gather and digitize items of religious significance from across the Shenandoah Valley so that they may be shared with the greater community via JMU Libraries. Community members were invited to East Campus Library (now Rose Library) from 10am to 2pm on Saturday, April 14, 2012 to share their items. The following excerpt from Dr. Witmer’s syllabus gives a better indication of both the class and the event’s purpose.
"Within the new field of digital history, historians have pioneered an innovative approach to collecting and studying the past. This class will adapt a model recently developed at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln and work with JMU Special Collections to organize and host our own History Harvest. This event invites community members to share their records related to the religious history of Virginia and the Shenandoah Valley for digital preservation and study by our class and future scholars. In regular consultation with the professor and Special Collections Librarian, students will use their skills and creativity to plan the History Harvest."
Scope and Content
The History Harvest Collection consists of 20.36 gigabytes of scanned files, approx. 615 pages of material. The items in this collection cover various communities, churches, and denominations within the Shenandoah Valley. The collection is arranged in series based upon the donor.
Series One: William Ney, 1880s to present, bulk 1923-1989, contains information about the Beth El Congregation. The items in this series tell the history of the Beth El Temple through photographs, manuscript, and newspapers, and were brought in from the temple archives.
Series Two: Martha Dofflemy, 1999-2012, contains information about Elkton Presbyterian Church.
Series Three: Kenneth J. Weaver, 1835-2012, bulk 1969-2012, pertains to Virginia Mennonites.
Series Four: Elwood Yoder, 1817-2010, contains two books, one about a Mennonite congregation in Broadway, Virginia, and another about a Mennonite bishop.
Series Five: Jane Desper, 1901-2001, pertains to White Hill Church of the Brethren.
Series Six: Esther Yoder Stenson, 1940s-1980s, contains items relating to the Amish church.
Series Seven: James Good, 1861, 1971 and undated, contains three Civil War photocopied documents.
Series Eight: Harold E. Huber, undated, contains a photograph of White House, which is south of Luray, VA.
Arrangement
The arrangement of series is as follows:
I: William Ney - Beth El Congregation, 1880s to present, bulk 1923-1989
II: Martha Dofflemy - Elkton Presbyterian Church, 1999-2012
III: Kenneth J. Weaver - Virginia Mennonites, 1835-2012, bulk 1969-2012
IV: Elwood Yoder - Virginia Mennonites, 1817-2012
V: Jane Desper - White Hill Church of the Brethren, 1901-2001
VI: Esther Yoder Stenson - Amish Church, 1940s-1980s
VII: James Good - Mennonite, 1861, 1971 and undated
VIII: Harold E. Huber - undated
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Public Affairs. "JMU Students Plan to 'Harvest Valley's Religous History."
Witmer, Andrew. "James Madison University History Harvest." Andrew Witmer
Location of Originals
Most artifacts were scanned and returned to the donors while others were given as a loan or donation to Special Collections
Separated Material
Two copyrighted items donated by Frances Scruby were separated from the collection and are shelved with the rare books in JMU Special Collections:
Emmanual Church. One Hundred Years Serving Our Lord: Emmanuel Episcopal Church Greenwood, Albemarle County, Virginia. Preface by Langhorne Gibson, Jr., [1960]
Scruby, Frances. Neve: Virginia's Thousandfold Man. Charlottesville, Virginia: Pietas Publications, 2010.
Contents List
- William Ney - Beth El Congregation, 1880s to present, bulk 1923-1989
  - Photographs
    - Old and Current Building Interior and Exterior
    - Original Temple
    - 1923 Confirmation of Rabbis
    - Mosaics, Temple, Torah scrolls
  - Rededication Service of Congregation in 1925
    Bulletin
  - Mosaic
    (Written Document, Newspaper Articles, Pictures)
  - 25th Anniversary Book
    (1989)
- Martha Dofflemy - Elkton Presbyterian Church, 1999-2012
  - Church Directory (Undated)
  - Church Publications
    - "Celebrating 100 years of God's love and Faithfulness: Elkton Presbyterian Church 1899-1999," 1999
    - "Crismons - An Explanation of the Symbols on the Chrismon Tree at Elkton PResbyterian Church, Elkton, Virginia," December, 2001
  - Photographs
    - Church
      (inside and outside)
    - Pastors
    - Advent Wreath
  - Letters
  - Church Bulletins
    - Weekly Bulletin 2012
  - Brochures
  - Scans of Newspaper Articles
- Kenneth J. Weaver - Virginia Mennonites, 1835-2012, bulk, 1969-2012
  - In Search of Faithfulness by Glendon L. Blosser
  - People of Peace by Gloria Y. Diener
  - Introduction to Virginia Mennonite Conference
    (VMC)
    - Letter from VMC Officer
    - Brochure identifying VMC current stance as a service organization
  - VA Mennonite Missions - 1919-1969, Holding Forth the Word of Life
  - Enlarging the Borders, 150 Years of Expansion by E. Richard Good (Published 1985)
  - Conference Minutes -
    Copies of the first recorded minutes from 1835, containing both the original German and a translation
  - Shenandoah Mennonite Historians' Newsletter
    - Winter 2012
      (Contains lists of all Mennonite groups in VA)
    - Spring 2012
      (Contains a sample of historical reporting done by the Shenandoah Mennonite Historians)
  - Brochures for Breneman Turner Mill
    (Owned by Valley brethren-Mennonite Heritage Center)
  - Congregational Histories
    - 1936-1986 Harrisonburg Mennonite Church, "Glimpses of our Past," 50th Anniversary Celebration, November 15th - 16th, 1986
    - 75th Anniversary/75 year history of Harrisonburg Mennonite Church
  - Samples of Brochures about VMC 2012 Activities
    - March 2012 of "Connections"
      (VMC Newsletter)
    - Announcement for VMC's 2012 Annual Assembly
- Elwood Yoder - Virginia Mennonites, 1817-2012
  - We're Marching to Zion: A History of Zion Mennonite Church, Broadway, Virginia, 1885-2010 by Elwood E. Yoder
    (2 paperback copies)
  - The Bishop's Letters: The Writings, Life and Times of Virginia Mennonite Bishop Martin Burkholder, 1817-1860 by Elwood E. Yoder
    (1 bound copy)
- Jane Desper - White Hill Church of the Brethren, 1901-2001
  - Photocopied Documents, 1901-2001
    (This file consists of a single pdf document which details the church's original establishment, lists previous pastors with photographs, and lists of donors and the amount donated
- Esther Yoder Stenson - Amish Church, 1940s-1980s
  - Images of Clothes, Black cap, white organdy cap and apron, white cap, black bonnet, beach bonnet cap
  - German Prayer Book
- James Good - Mennonite1861, 1971 and Undated
  - Reprint of Mennonite Historical Bulletin article
  - Military Induction of Christian Good
  - Military Discharge of Christian Good
- Harold E. Huber, Undated
  - Photograph of White House
    (south of Luray, VA)